Architecture Governance Copilot is our Accelerate 3.0
proof of concept from Two Tokens One Brain.
It turns architecture work into an accountable,
AI-assisted governance record.
Product Owners and development teams prepare
the Solution Intent in Confluence.
An Azure DevOps governance ticket tracks the review.
A Domain Architect reviews through Teams meetings
and revision rounds.
This proof of concept uses synthetic local content
representing those sources.
Those handoffs scatter decisions, risks,
actions, and evidence.
Teams then rebuild the governance record manually.
AI synthesizes confirmed project context
into a draft Solution Intent.
It interprets the SI and transcript into structured,
evidence-linked governance proposals.
Humans retain control.
The target front end runs in Service Bench;
backend API and governed state run in SKE.
Permission-aware Confluence, Teams, and Azure DevOps connectors
retrieve only sources selected by the user.
Azure Repos supplies the chosen repository and branch;
Azure Boards supplies governance metadata.
The backend builds a context package for human confirmation;
only that approved scope reaches AI Factory, or AIF.
The application opens at Project Context,
the first of five visible stages.
The fictional workspace shows its ADO reference,
SI template, and repository branch.
It also shows supporting documents
and source-selection controls.
In production, permission-aware connectors retrieve
only user-confirmed sources.
Here, deterministic synthetic fixtures keep
the demonstration reliable and offline.
I inspect each preview, refresh the context,
and explicitly confirm the package.
Generate SI Draft validates confirmed context
before AI-assisted drafting.
It creates an editable proposal,
with source details available beneath it.
This is a drafting aid,
not publication or approval.
I confirm the draft before continuing.
The confirmed SI is preserved with the matching
Teams-style transcript and review metadata.
Analyze Review starts AI-assisted analysis
of the review evidence.
A separate Human Review page opens
with a Changes Requested outcome.
The summary covers decisions, findings, risk, actions,
an open question, and missing information.
The decision accepts managed PostgreSQL
as the system of record.
The proposals identify unresolved failover,
resilience, and support-ownership evidence.
They also identify a capacity risk.
Every proposal retains a source quote from
the Solution Intent, transcript, or both.
The reviewer can inspect evidence, edit fields,
and include or exclude items.
I change the first action owner
to the synthetic value Taylor Kim.
Then I exclude the unresolved Redis question.
Evidence stays read-only.
That human checkpoint is essential: AI proposes
structure and evidence links.
It does not decide the outcome,
approve architecture, or publish records.
The Domain Architect and project team
retain accountability.
Only after human review do I confirm the record
and generate outputs.
The completed package preserves those choices in the
review record and Azure DevOps work-item previews.
Nothing was submitted to Azure DevOps.
AI reduces first-pass drafting
and review administration.
Evidence grounding makes every proposal
easier to verify.
Every record remains human-reviewed, and authority
stays with the Domain Architect.
Architecture Governance Copilot creates a
human-controlled path from governed context,
through AI assistance, to accountable action.
Two Tokens One Brain.