Architecture Governance Copilot is our Accelerate 3.0
proof of concept from Two Tokens One Brain.
It turns architecture work into an accountable,
evidence-backed governance record.
Product Owners and development teams prepare
the Solution Intent using a required template.
The official document remains in Confluence,
and an Azure DevOps ticket tracks the review.
A Domain Architect reviews it through Teams meetings
and revision rounds.
This proof of concept uses synthetic local content
representing those sources.
Those handoffs scatter decisions, risks,
actions, and evidence.
Teams then rebuild the governance record manually.
The Copilot drafts the SI, structures its review,
preserves evidence, and keeps humans in control.
Target architecture deploys the front end in Service Bench
and backend API in SKE.
Controlled adapters connect Confluence, Teams, AIF LLM,
database, and Azure DevOps.
The application opens at Draft Solution Intent,
the first of four visible stages.
Demo mode uses synthetic data, local processing,
and no external connections.
I load the SI template, selected source-code context,
and supporting notes for a fictional service.
Generate SI Draft validates that context
and creates an editable draft.
This is a drafting aid, not publication or approval.
I explicitly confirm the draft.
The application then moves to Review Inputs,
preserving the confirmed Solution Intent.
I add the matching Teams-style transcript
and review metadata, then select Analyze Review.
A separate Human Review page opens
with a Changes Requested outcome.
The summary shows one decision, three findings,
one risk, two actions, and one open question,
plus two missing-information items.
The decision accepts managed PostgreSQL
as the system of record.
Findings identify missing traffic-failover behaviour,
missing RTO and RPO values,
and undefined production support ownership.
Database sizing is a release risk.
Each item retains a source quote from
the Solution Intent, transcript, or both.
This remains a proposal, not an approval.
The reviewer can inspect evidence, edit fields,
and include or exclude items.
I change the first action owner
to the synthetic value Taylor Kim,
then exclude the unresolved Redis question.
Evidence stays read-only.
Only after human review do I confirm the record
and generate outputs.
The completed package preserves those choices:
Taylor Kim appears in the review record
and first Azure DevOps work-item preview,
while the Redis question is absent.
The output is preview-only;
nothing was submitted to Azure DevOps.
This workflow reduces manual review administration
and supports more consistent records.
It also improves evidence traceability.
Every record remains human-reviewed, and authority
stays with the Domain Architect.
Architecture Governance Copilot demonstrates
a practical, human-controlled path
from architecture context to accountable action.
Two Tokens One Brain.