Architecture Governance Copilot is our Accelerate 3.0
proof of concept from Two Tokens One Brain.
It turns architecture review discussion into
an accountable, evidence-backed record.
Product Owners and development teams prepare
the Solution Intent using the required template.
The official SI remains in Confluence,
with an ADO governance ticket for review tracking.
A Domain Architect reviews it through Teams meetings
and revision rounds until formal approval.
Here, synthetic Confluence content
is normalized into Markdown,
while synthetic text represents a Teams review transcript
produced only when transcription is enabled.
That process creates repeated administration.
Decisions, findings, risks, and actions can be spread
across the SI, meeting discussion, notes, and ADO.
Teams manually rebuild the governance record
and tracked work,
increasing the risk that evidence, ownership,
or requested changes are missed or inconsistent.
The Copilot structures both normalized inputs,
preserves evidence,
and pauses for human review before producing
a standardized record and mock ADO actions.
It never approves automatically.
The application begins with clear synthetic-data
and human-accountability notices.
I load the bundled review package: version 1.2
of a fictional Digital Payment Notification Service SI,
review metadata, and a timestamped transcript.
Analyze Review validates both sources
and opens a separate Human Review page.
The outcome is Changes Requested.
The summary shows one decision, three findings,
one risk, two actions, one open question,
and two missing-information items.
The decision accepts managed PostgreSQL
as the system of record.
Findings identify missing traffic-failover behaviour,
missing RTO and RPO values,
and undefined production support ownership.
Database sizing is a release risk.
Every item retains a source quote
from the SI, the transcript, or both.
This is a proposal, not an approval.
The reviewer can inspect evidence, edit fields,
and include or exclude items.
I change the first action owner
to the clearly synthetic value Taylor Kim,
then exclude the unresolved Redis question.
Evidence stays read-only.
Only now do I confirm the reviewed record
and generate outputs.
The application preserves those choices:
Taylor Kim appears in the review record
and first mock work item,
while the Redis question is absent.
Two mock Azure DevOps actions are prepared,
and the screen confirms that
no real work item was created.
This workflow reduces manual review administration
and supports more consistent records.
It helps reduce the risk of missed findings and actions,
and improves evidence traceability.
Structured outputs can support future integration,
but every record is reviewed before generation,
and formal decision authority remains
with the Domain Architect.
The extractor interface uses a deterministic
demo implementation for reliable offline use.
It does not analyze arbitrary documents
or use a production enterprise LLM.
A future approved provider could connect
Confluence, Teams, and Azure DevOps;
none exists today.
Architecture Governance Copilot shows one practical,
human-controlled path from architecture discussion
to accountable action.
Two Tokens One Brain.